<?xml version="1.0"?>
<articles>
<article>
	<author>A. Barmpoutis, N. Nikolaides, and I. Pittas</author>
	<title>Face 3D Pose Estimation Using a Generic 3D Face Model and Facial Feature Extraction</title>
	<journal>In Proceedings of PCI2003: Panhellenic Conference in Informatics</journal>
	<urlvenue>http://skyblue.csd.auth.gr/~bci1/</urlvenue>
	<month>21-23 November</month>
	<volume></volume>
	<number></number>
	<year>2003</year>
	<pages>519-526</pages>
	<urlpdf></urlpdf>
	<abstract>In this paper an algorithm that processes a video sequence for humean face 3D pose estimation, is presented. The procedure that is followed is described briefly below. In the beginning, facial features are extracted for each frame. Afterwards, these are used in order to make an initial estimation of their position in 3D space. The results produced are optimized, either by taking into consideration anthropometric features, or by using a 3D model of the human face. In that way, the initial prediction is greately improved and the resulting accuracy is more than satisfactory. Such rechniques could process videos displaying news, journalists, actors or even people in general, or even be used in object-based techniques for video coding (eg. MPEG-4), in machine vision applications and in human computer interaction enviroments.</abstract>
	<selected></selected>
	<image>paper2.jpg</image>
	<type>c</type>
	<area>3dcv</area>
</article>
<article>
	<author>J. Barker, and A. Barmpoutis</author>
	<title>Smart dust: Monte Carlo simulation of self-organised transport</title>
	<journal>In Proceedings of IWCE04: 10th IEEE International Workshop on Computational Electronics</journal>
	<urlvenue>http://www.iwce.nanohub.org/</urlvenue>
	<month>24-27 October</month>
	<volume></volume>
	<number></number>
	<year>2004</year>
	<pages>182-183</pages>
	<urlpdf>http://ieeexplore.ieee.org/iel5/9657/30514/01407387.pdf</urlpdf>
	<abstract></abstract>
	<selected></selected>
	<image>paper3.jpg</image>
	<type>a</type>
	<area>other</area>
</article>
<article>
	<author>J. Barker, and A. Barmpoutis</author>
	<title>Smart Dust: Monte Carlo Simulation of Self-Organised Transport</title>
	<journal>Journal of Computational Electronics</journal>
	<urlvenue>http://www.ingentaconnect.com/content/klu/jcel/2004/00000003/f0020003</urlvenue>
	<month>October</month>
	<volume>3</volume>
	<number>3-4</number>
	<year>2004</year>
	<pages>317-321</pages>
	<urlpdf>http://www.ingentaconnect.com/content/klu/jcel/2004/00000003/F0020003/00007068</urlpdf>
	<abstract>Smart dust is envisaged as swarms of miniature communication/sensor devices useful for remote monitoring in space exploration. With diameters and densities comparable to sand particles the behaviour of passive dust will be identical to the movement of airborne sand. Here we examine algorithms for the adaptive shape change of smart dust modes that permits a change in drag coefficient depending on whether or not the random motion is in a favourable direction. Monte Carlo simulations are reported for swarms of smart dust devices transporting in the wind-dominated environment of the Martian landscape. It is concluded that relatively simple shape changing algorithms, activated through an electro-active polymer sheath, will permit self-organised transport over large distances.</abstract>
	<selected></selected>
	<image>paper4.jpg</image>
	<type>j</type>
	<area>other</area>
</article>
<article>
	<author>A. Barmpoutis, J. Barker</author>
	<title>Self-organized Transportation System of Smart Dust Distributed Sensors</title>
	<journal>ICDSNS05: Innovations and Commercial Applications of Distributed Sensor Networks Symposia</journal>
	<urlvenue></urlvenue>
	<month>18-19 October</month>
	<volume></volume>
	<number></number>
	<year>2005</year>
	<pages></pages>
	<urlpdf></urlpdf>
	<abstract></abstract>
	<selected></selected>
	<image>paper5.jpg</image>
	<type>a</type>
	<area>other</area>
</article>
<article>
	<author>A. Barmpoutis</author>
	<title>Morphological Neural Networks with Orthonormal Basis Dendrites</title>
	<journal>ACMSE06: ACM Southeast Conference</journal>
	<urlvenue>http://acmse2006.cs.fit.edu/</urlvenue>
	<month>10-12 March</month>
	<volume></volume>
	<number></number>
	<year>2006</year>
	<pages>244-248</pages>
	<urlpdf></urlpdf>
	<abstract></abstract>
	<selected></selected>
	<image>paper6.jpg</image>
	<type>c</type>
	<area>nn</area>
</article>
<article>
	<author>A. Barmpoutis, B. C. Vemuri, T. M. Shepherd, and J. R. Forder</author>
	<title>Robust Interpolation of DT-MRI Data Using Tensor Splines</title>
	<journal>ISMRM06: Scientific Meeting of International Society for Magnetic Resonance in Medicine</journal>
	<urlvenue>http://www.ismrm.org/06/</urlvenue>
	<month>6-12 May</month>
	<volume></volume>
	<number></number>
	<year>2006</year>
	<pages></pages>
	<urlpdf></urlpdf>
	<abstract></abstract>
	<selected></selected>
	<image>paper7.jpg</image>
	<type>a</type>
	<area>dti</area>
</article>
<article>
	<author>S. Chandra, K. Padgett, A. Barmpoutis, J. R. Forder</author>
	<title>First Report of Diffusion Tensor Imaging of the Murine Eye</title>
	<journal>ISMRM06: Scientific Meeting of International Society for Magnetic Resonance in Medicine</journal>
	<urlvenue>http://www.ismrm.org/06/</urlvenue>
	<month>6-12 May</month>
	<volume></volume>
	<number></number>
	<year>2006</year>
	<pages></pages>
	<urlpdf></urlpdf>
	<abstract></abstract>
	<selected></selected>
	<image>paper8.jpg</image>
	<type>a</type>
	<area>dti</area>
</article>
<article>
	<author>A. Barmpoutis, and G. X. Ritter</author>
	<title>Orthonormal Basis Latice Neural Networks</title>
	<journal>In Proceedings of FUZZ06: International Conference on Fuzzy Systems</journal>
	<urlvenue>http://www.wcci2006.org/</urlvenue>
	<month>16-21 July</month>
	<volume></volume>
	<number></number>
	<year>2006</year>
	<pages>331-336</pages>
	<urlpdf>barmpoutis_fuzz06.pdf</urlpdf>
	<abstract>Lattice based neural networks are capable of resolving some difficult non-linear problems and have been successfully employed to solve real-world problems. In this paper a novel model of a lattice neural network (LNN) is presented. This new model generalizes the standard basis lattice neural network (SB-LNN) based on dendritic computing. In particular, we show how each neural dendrite can work on a different orthonormal basis than the other dendrites. We present experimental results that demonstrate superior learning performance of the new Orthonormal Basis Lattice Neural Network (OB-LNN) over SB-LNNs.</abstract>
	<selected></selected>
	<image>paper10.jpg</image>
	<type>c</type>
	<area>nn</area>
</article>
<article>
	<author>A. Barmpoutis, B. C. Vemuri, and J. R. Forder</author>
	<title>Robust Tensor Splines for Approximation of Diffusion Tensor MRI Data</title>
	<journal>In Proceedings of MMBIA06: IEEE Computer Society Workshop on 
 Mathematical Methods in Biomedical Image Analysis</journal>
	<urlvenue>http://groups.csail.mit.edu/vision/mmbia/</urlvenue>
	<month>17-18 June</month>
	<volume></volume>
	<number></number>
	<year>2006</year>
	<pages>86-86</pages>
	<urlpdf>barmpoutis_mmbia06.pdf</urlpdf>
	<abstract>In this paper, we present a novel and robust spline approximation algorithm given a noisy symmetric positive definite (SPD) tensor field. Such tensor fields commonly arise in the field of Medical Imaging in the form of Diffusion Tensor (DT) MRI data sets. We develop a statistically robust algorithm for constructing a tensor product of B-splines - for approximating and interpolating these data - using the Riemannian metric of the manifold of SPD tensors. Our method involves a two step procedure wherein the first step uses Riemannian distances in order to evaluate a tensor spline by computing a weighted intrinsic average of diffusion tensors and the second step involves minimization of the Riemannian distance between the evaluated spline curve and the given data. These two steps are alternated to achieve the desired tensor spline approximation to the given tensor field. We present comparisons of our algorithm with four existing methods of tensor interpolation applied to DT-MRI data from fixed heart slices of a rabbit, and show significantly improved results in the presence of noise and outliers. We also present validation results for our algorithm using synthetically generated noisy tensor field data with outliers. This interpolation work has many applications e.g., in DT-MRI registration, in DT-MRI Atlas construction etc. This research was in part funded by the NIH ROI NS42075 and the Department of Radiology, University of Florida.</abstract>
	<selected></selected>
	<image>paper9.jpg</image>
	<type>c</type>
	<area>dti</area>
</article>
<article>
	<author>A. Barmpoutis, and G. X. Ritter</author>
	<title>Orthonormal Basis Latice Neural Networks</title>
	<journal>In Computational Intelligence Based on LatticeTheory, V. Kaburlasos and G. X. Ritter (ed.)</journal>
	<urlvenue>http://www.springer.com/east/home/engineering?SGWID=5-175-22-173740622-0</urlvenue>
	<month>Springer-Verlag, Heidelberg, Germany,</month>
	<volume></volume>
	<number></number>
	<year>2007</year>
	<pages>43-56</pages>
	<urlpdf>barmpoutis_latticebook07.pdf</urlpdf>
	<abstract>Lattice based neural networks are capable of resolving some difficult non-linear problems and have been successfully employed to solve real-world problems. In this paper a novel model of a lattice neural network (LNN) is presented. This new model generalizes the standard basis lattice neural network (SB-LNN) based on dendritic computing. In particular, we show how each neural dendrite can work on a different orthonormal basis than the other dendrites. We present experimental results that demonstrate superior learning performance of the new Orthonormal Basis Lattice Neural Network (OB-LNN) over SB-LNNs.</abstract>
	<selected></selected>
	<image>paper11.jpg</image>
	<type>bc</type>
	<area>nn</area>
</article>
<article>
	<author>A. Barmpoutis, and J. R. Barker</author>
	<title>Autonomous smart dust clusters for remote planetary exploration</title>
	<journal>In Proceedings of RAS National Astronomy Meeting</journal>
	<urlvenue>http://www.nam2007.uclan.ac.uk/</urlvenue>
	<month>16-20 April</month>
	<volume></volume>
	<number></number>
	<year>2007</year>
	<pages>105-106</pages>
	<urlpdf></urlpdf>
	<abstract>Smart dust is envisaged as swarms of miniature communication/sensor devices useful for remote monitoring in space exploration. Very similar nanotechnology systems, known as "smart specks" are already being fabricated at the University of Glasgow Nanoelectronics Research Centre for applications in collective computer intelligence, wireless distributed systems and smart RF-ID tagging. With diameters and densities comparable to sand particles the behaviour of passive "dust" is comparable to the movement of airborne sand. A possible application would involve the launch of several tens of thousands of smart dust elements into a wind borne environment. The subsequent mission would involve navigation and data gathering/sensing over a period of time. Finally, the surviving "dust" would re-grouping into a phased array for transmission of data back to a remote spacecraft. The central problem is how to arrange for the collective self-organised motion of the smart dust ensemble in the presence of hostile terrain and weather. We have investigated the possibility of dynamically changing the shape of the smart dust elements so as to permit controlled navigation. Here we examine algorithms for the adaptive shape change of smart dust modes that permits a change in drag coefficient depending on whether or not the random motion is in a favourable direction. Monte Carlo simulations are reported for swarms of smart dust devices transporting in the wind-dominated environment of the Martian landscape. It is concluded that relatively simple shape changing algorithms, activated through an electro-active polymer sheath, will permit self-organised transport over large distances.</abstract>
	<selected></selected>
	<image>paper1.jpg</image>
	<type>a</type>
	<area>other</area>
</article>
<article>
	<author>A. Barmpoutis, E. Bozia and R. S. Wagman</author>
	<title>Application of 3D Technologies for the Analysis of Ancient Inscriptions</title>
	<journal>In Proceedings of CIEGL07: 13th International Congress of Greek and Latin Epigraphy, Oxford</journal>
	<urlvenue>http://ciegl.classics.ox.ac.uk</urlvenue>
	<month>2 - 7 Sep</month>
	<volume></volume>
	<number></number>
	<year>2007</year>
	<pages></pages>
	<urlpdf></urlpdf>
	<abstract>In this paper we propose a novel method for 3D reconstruction of inscriptions using a
shape-from-shading technique and for statistical analysis of their reconstructed surfaces using images of scanned squeezes.
The squeeze is scanned twice from two different directions. Using the shading information a 3D model of the original 
surface is reconstructed and parametrized as a height map. This map is automatically segmented into smaller regions 
containing single letters, which are divided into groups of same characters and are further employed for a statistical 
analysis of the inscribed letters. The results can be used for studying the variations of the lettering techniques 
within a set of inscriptions.We have applied our framework to five inscribed fragments from the archaeological site of 
Epidauros, containing religious hymns for Asclepius and other deities (IG IV I 2, 129-135; SEG 30, 390 = Robert Wagman, 
Inni di Epidauro, 1995). Although found in different locations, these inscriptions show close affinities in content 
(sacred poetry), material (red local limestone) and writing (uncial lettering of the third century CE).
The 3D reconstruction of the letterforms provides us with definite proof that all of them came from the same 
monument, possibly an inscribed wall from one of the buildings in the sanctuary's main area. A closer 
observation of the results reveals even some minor groups of letters with similar construction, which 
validates the accuracy of the proposed method. The advantages of 3D reconstruction in epigraphical research 
are especially obvious in the case of badly weathered or damaged inscribed surfaces, where the lettering is 
difficult to discern with the naked eye. A demo of this method can be found in: <a href="http://plaza.ufl.edu/bozia/epigraphy">
http://plaza.ufl.edu/bozia/epigraphy</a></abstract>
	<selected></selected>
	<image>paper20.jpg</image>
	<type>a</type>
	<area>dh</area>
</article>
<article>
	<author>S. Chandra, A. Barmpoutis, and J. R. Forder</author>
	<title>Diffusion Tensor Imaging detects and quantifies changes in preambility in the murine</title>
	<journal>ISMRM07: Scientific Meeting of International Society for Magnetic Resonance in Medicine</journal>
	<urlvenue>http://www.ismrm.org/07/</urlvenue>
	<month>19-25 May</month>
	<volume></volume>
	<number></number>
	<year>2007</year>
	<pages></pages>
	<urlpdf></urlpdf>
	<abstract></abstract>
	<selected></selected>
	<image>paper1.jpg</image>
	<type>a</type>
	<area>dti</area>
</article>
<article>
	<author>M. Hwang, M. Clark, A. Barmpoutis, and J. Forder</author>
	<title>Contribution of myocardial vascular compartment to water diffusion</title>
	<journal>ISMRM07: Scientific Meeting of International Society for Magnetic Resonance in Medicine</journal>
	<urlvenue>http://www.ismrm.org/07/</urlvenue>
	<month>19-25 May</month>
	<volume></volume>
	<number></number>
	<year>2007</year>
	<pages></pages>
	<urlpdf></urlpdf>
	<abstract></abstract>
	<selected></selected>
	<image>paper1.jpg</image>
	<type>a</type>
	<area>dti</area>
</article>
<article>
	<author>A. Barmpoutis, B. C. Vemuri</author>
	<title>Exponential Diffusion Tensors for efficient higher-order DT-MRI computations</title>
	<journal>ISMRM07: Scientific Meeting of International Society for Magnetic Resonance in Medicine</journal>
	<urlvenue>http://www.ismrm.org/07/</urlvenue>
	<month>19-25 May</month>
	<volume></volume>
	<number></number>
	<year>2007</year>
	<pages></pages>
	<urlpdf></urlpdf>
	<abstract></abstract>
	<selected></selected>
	<image>paper1.jpg</image>
	<type>a</type>
	<area>dti</area>
</article>
<article>
	<author>A. Barmpoutis, S. Chandra, J. R. Forder and B. C. Vemuri</author>
	<title>A novel DTI method for analyzing the diffusion of water in retina</title>
	<journal>ISMRM07: Scientific Meeting of International Society for Magnetic Resonance in Medicine</journal>
	<urlvenue>http://www.ismrm.org/07/</urlvenue>
	<month>19-25 May</month>
	<volume></volume>
	<number></number>
	<year>2007</year>
	<pages></pages>
	<urlpdf></urlpdf>
	<abstract>In this paper, we present a novel DTI method for analyzing the diffusion of water in retina. Studies on DTI datasets from mouse
eyes have shown that the diffusivity in the layer of retina has an organized structure. In this work, we analyze this structure by
evaluating a quantitative measure using the following method. We represent each diffusion tensor of the retinal layer by a multivariate
Gaussian probability, whose isosurfaces have the same orientations as the primary eigenvector of the corresponding diffusion tensor. The
weighted sum of these probabilities formulates a mixture of Gaussians. In our experimental results we show that this mixture of
Gaussians takes its global maximum value near the center of the eye (focal point). In our experiments we used 3D DTI datasets acquired
from three normal mouse eyes, and an additional one eye that was subjected to focal laser treatment, resulting in disruption of the BRB. In
the latter dataset the global maximum of the probability is far from the center of the eye, as a result of the changes in the diffusion properties.</abstract>
	<selected></selected>
	<image>paper16.jpg</image>
	<type>a</type>
	<area>dti</area>
</article>
<article>
	<author>A. Barmpoutis, B. Jian, B. C. Vemuri and T. M. Shepherd</author>
	<title>Symmetric Positive 4th Order Tensors &amp; their Estimation from Diffusion Weighted MRI</title>
	<journal>In LNCS 4584 (Springer) Proceedings of IPMI07: Information Processing in Medical Imaging</journal>
	<urlvenue>http://www2.wiau.man.ac.uk/caws/Conferences/40/index.html</urlvenue>
	<month>2-6 July</month>
	<volume></volume>
	<number></number>
	<year>2007</year>
	<pages>308-319</pages>
	<urlpdf>barmpoutis_ipmi07_lncs.pdf</urlpdf>
	<abstract>In Diffusion Weighted Magnetic Resonance Image (DW-MRI)
processing a 2nd order tensor has been commonly used to approximate
the diffusivity function at each lattice point of the DW-MRI data. It is
now well known that this 2nd-order approximation fails to approximate
complex local tissue structures, such as fibers crossings. In this paper
we employ a 4th order symmetric positive semi-definite (PSD) tensor
approximation to represent the diffusivity function and present a novel
technique to estimate these tensors from the DW-MRI data guaranteeing
the PSD property. There have been several published articles in literature
on higher order tensor approximations of the diffusivity function
but none of them guarantee the positive semi-definite constraint, which
is a fundamental constraint since negative values of the diffusivity coefficients
are not meaningful. In our methods, we parameterize the 4th
order tensors as a sum of squares of quadratic forms by using the so called
Gram matrix method from linear algebra and its relation to the Hilbert's
theorem on ternary quartics. This parametric representation is then used
in a nonlinear-least squares formulation to estimate the PSD tensors of
order 4 from the data. We define a metric for the higher-order tensors
and employ it for regularization across the lattice. Finally, performance
of this model is depicted on synthetic data as well as real DW-MRI from
an isolated rat hippocampus.</abstract>
	<selected></selected>
	<image>paper18.jpg</image>
	<type>c</type>
	<area>dti</area>
</article>
<article>
	<author>A. Barmpoutis, and B. C. Vemuri</author>
	<title>Exponential Tensors: A framework for efficient higher-order DT-MRI computations</title>
	<journal>In Proceedings of ISBI07: IEEE International Symposium on Biomedical Imaging</journal>
	<urlvenue>http://www.biomedicalimaging.org/</urlvenue>
	<month>12-15 April</month>
	<volume></volume>
	<number></number>
	<year>2007</year>
	<pages>792-795</pages>
	<urlpdf>barmpoutis_isbi07.pdf</urlpdf>
	<abstract>In Diffusion Tensor Magnetic Resonance Image (DT-MRI) processing a 2nd order tensor has been commonly used to approximate the diffusivity function at each lattice point of the 3D volume image. These tensors are symmetric positive definite matrices and the appropriate constraints required in algorithms for processing them makes these algorithms complex and significantly increases their computational complexity. In this paper we present a novel parameterization of the diffusivity function using which the positive definite property of the function is guaranteed without any increase in computation. This parameterization can be used for any order tensor approximations; we present Cartesian tensor approximations of order 2, 4, 6 and 8 respectively, of the diffusivity function all of which retain the positivity property in this parameterization without the need for any explicit enforcement. Furthermore, we present an efficient framework for computing distances and geodesics in the space of the coefficients of our proposed diffusivity function. Distances &amp; geodesics are useful for performing interpolation, computation of statistics etc. on high rank positive definite tensors. We validate our model using real diffusion weighted MR data from excised, perfusion-fixed rat optic chiasm.</abstract>
	<selected></selected>
	<image>paper12.jpg</image>
	<type>c</type>
	<area>dti</area>
</article>
<article>
	<author>A. Barmpoutis, B. C. Vemuri and J. R. Forder</author>
	<title>Registration of High Angular Resolution Diffusion MRI Images using 4th Order Tensors</title>
	<journal>In LNCS 4791, v.1 (Springer) Proceedings of MICCAI07: Int. Conf. on Medical Image Computing and Computer Assisted Intervention</journal>
	<urlvenue>http://www.miccai2007.org</urlvenue>
	<month>29 Oct - 2 Nov</month>
	<volume></volume>
	<number></number>
	<year>2007</year>
	<pages>908-915</pages>
	<urlpdf>barmpoutis_miccai07_lncs.pdf</urlpdf>
	<abstract>Registration of Diffusion Weighted (DW)-MRI datasets has
been commonly achieved to date in literature by using either scalar or
2nd-order tensorial information. However, scalar or 2nd-order tensors fail
to capture complex local tissue structures, such as fiber crossings, and
therefore, datasets containing fiber-crossings cannot be registered accurately
 by using these techniques. In this paper we present a novel method
for non-rigidly registering DW-MRI datasets that are represented by a
field of 4th-order tensors. We use the Hellinger distance between the
normalized 4th-order tensors represented as distributions, in order to
achieve this registration. Hellinger distance is easy to compute, is scale
and rotation invariant and hence allows for comparison of the true shape
of distributions. Furthermore, we propose a novel 4th-order tensor re-
transformation operator, which plays an essential role in the registration
procedure and shows significantly better performance compared to the
re-orientation operator used in literature for DTI registration. We val-
idate and compare our technique with other existing scalar image and
DTI registration methods using simulated diffusion MR data and real
HARDI datasets.</abstract>
	<selected></selected>
	<image>paper19.jpg</image>
	<type>c</type>
	<area>dti</area>
</article>
<article>
	<author>A. Barmpoutis, B. C. Vemuri, T. M. Shepherd, and J. R. Forder</author>
	<title>Tensor splines for interpolation and approximation of DT-MRI with applications to segmentation of isolated rat hippocampi</title>
	<journal>IEEE TMI: Transactions on Medical Imaging</journal>
	<urlvenue>http://www.ieee-tmi.org/</urlvenue>
	<month>November</month>
	<volume>26</volume>
	<number>11</number>
	<year>2007</year>
	<pages>1537-1546</pages>
	<urlpdf>barmpoutis_tmi07.pdf</urlpdf>
	<abstract>In this paper, we present novel algorithms for statistically robust interpolation and approximation of diffusion
tensors - which are symmetric positive definite (SPD) matrices - and use them in developing a significant extension
to an existing probabilistic algorithm for scalar field segmentation, in order to segment DT-MRI data sets.
Using the Riemannian metric on the space of SPD matrices, we present a novel and robust higher order (cubic)
continuous tensor product of B-splines algorithm to approximate the SPD diffusion tensor fields. The resulting
approximations are appropriately dubbed tensor splines. Next, we segment the diffusion tensor field by jointly
estimating the label (assigned to each voxel) field, which is modeled by a Gauss Markov Measure Field (GMMF)
and the parameters of each smooth tensor spline model representing the labeled regions. Results of interpolation,
approximation and segmentation are presented for synthetic data and real diffusion tensor fields from an isolated
rat hippocampus, along with validation. We also present comparisons of our algorithms with existing methods
and show significantly improved results in the presence of noise as well as outliers.
<br/><b>Tensor Spline DEMO:[<a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=kXizjVPXn4k">Click here</a>]</b>
</abstract>
	<selected></selected>
	<image>paper17.jpg</image>
	<type>j</type>
	<area>dti</area>
</article>
<article>
	<author>Saurav B. Chandra, Angelos Barmpoutis and John R. Forder</author>
	<title>Diffusion Tensor Imaging detects and characterizes Proliferative Diabetic Retinopathy in the Murine Retina</title>
	<journal>In Proceedings of ENC08: 49th Experimental Nuclear Magnetic Resonance Conference</journal>
	<urlvenue>http://www.enc-conference.org/</urlvenue>
	<month>9 - 14 March</month>
	<volume></volume>
	<number></number>
	<year>2008</year>
	<pages></pages>
	<urlpdf></urlpdf>
	<abstract>Diabetic Retinopathy is one of the foremost pathologies related to blindness. Its major characteristic is the breakdown of the blood-retinal barrier (BRB), thus increasing its permeability. We have previously detected and quantified changes in the retina using DTI. In this study we track retinal damage using DTI in the retinas of control, lasered (focal lesion) and Type I diabetic eyes. The fractional anisotropy (FA) for each of these conditions was observed to be significantly different. Future studies will involve in vivo imaging of mice at various stages of the disease. This may provide the means for early diagnosis of diabetic retinopathy using DTI.</abstract>
	<selected></selected>
	<image>paper1.jpg</image>
	<type>a</type>
	<area>dti</area>
</article>
<article>
	<author>Saurav B. Chandra, Angelos Barmpoutis and John R. Forder</author>
	<title>Diffusion Tensor Imaging detects and characterizes Proliferative Diabetic Retinopathy in the Murine Retina</title>
	<journal>ISMRM08: Scientific Meeting of International Society for Magnetic Resonance in Medicine</journal>
	<urlvenue>http://www.ismrm.org/08/</urlvenue>
	<month>3 - 9 May</month>
	<volume></volume>
	<number></number>
	<year>2008</year>
	<pages></pages>
	<urlpdf></urlpdf>
	<abstract>Diabetic retinopathy is the most severe of the various other ocular
problems associated with diabetes and still remains one of the foremost causes of
blindness in the world. The phenomenon that initiates this condition is the
breakdown of the blood-retinal barrier (BRB) and neovascularization or
angiogenesis around the retina resulting from hypoxia which is triggered by
vascular endothelial growth factor (VEGF). In our previous endeavors we have
been able to successfully detect and quantify changes in the retina using diffusion
tensor imaging.
The specific aim in this study is to prove that the alterations in the eye following
damage (by laser damage and diabetic retinopathy) can be detected by DTI. This is
done by comparing the fractional anisotropies in the retinas of controls versus
diabetic eyes. Before using actual diabetic eyes, we used mouse eyes subjected to a
laser injury as a model for diabetic eyes since the laser procedure alters the BRB
permeability comparable to diabetic retinopathy. This was followed by imaging
eyes with diabetic retinopathy. The mice had been subjected to Type I diabetes.
Both sets of experiments were successful in determining significant differences
between the fractional anisotropies of retinas in controls compared to the lasered as
well as diabetic retinas. Future studies will involve in vivo imaging of mice with
various stages of the disease. In vivo imaging of control mice has been accomplished
previously. This will ultimately lead to early diagnosis of the disease using DTI.</abstract>
	<selected></selected>
	<image>paper1.jpg</image>
	<type>a</type>
	<area>dti</area>
</article>
<article>
	<author>A. Barmpoutis, B. C. Vemuri and J. R. Forder</author>
	<title>Fast displacement probability profile approximation from HARDI using 4th-order tensors</title>
	<journal>In Proceedings of ISBI08: IEEE International Symposium on Biomedical Imaging</journal>
	<urlvenue>http://www.biomedicalimaging.org</urlvenue>
	<month>14 - 17 May</month>
	<volume></volume>
	<number></number>
	<year>2008</year>
	<pages>911-914</pages>
	<urlpdf>barmpoutis_isbi08.pdf</urlpdf>
	<abstract>Cartesian tensor basis have been widely used to approximate spherical functions. In Medical Imaging, tensors of various orders
have been used to model the diffusivity function in Diffusion-weighted MRI data sets. However, it is known that the peaks of the diffusivity do not correspond to orientations of the underlying fibers and hence the displacement probability profiles should be employed instead. In this paper, we present a novel representation of the probability profile by a 4th order tensor, which is a smooth spherical function that can approximate single-fibers as well as multiple-fiber structures. We also present a method for efficiently estimating the unknown tensor coefficients of the probability profile directly from a given high-angular resolution diffusion-weighted (HARDI) data set. The accuracy of our model is validated by experiments on synthetic and real HARDI datasets from a fixed rat spinal cord.</abstract>
	<selected></selected>
	<image>paper21.jpg</image>
	<type>c</type>
	<area>dti</area>
</article>
<article>
	<author>R. Kumar, A. Barmpoutis, B. C. Vemuri, P. R. Carney and T. H. Mareci</author>
	<title>Multi-Fiber Reconstruction from DW-MRI using a Continuous Mixture of von
Mises-Fisher Distributions</title>
	<journal>In Proceedings of MMBIA08: IEEE Computer Society Workshop on 
 Mathematical Methods in Biomedical Image Analysis</journal>
	<urlvenue>http://vision.eecs.ucf.edu/</urlvenue>
	<month>24 - 26 June</month>
	<volume></volume>
	<number></number>
	<year>2008</year>
	<pages>1-8</pages>
	<urlpdf>barmpoutis_mmbia08.pdf</urlpdf>
	<abstract>In this paper we propose a method for reconstructing the
Diffusion Weighted Magnetic Resonance (DW-MR) signal
at each lattice point using a novel continuousmixture of von
Mises-Fisher distribution functions. Unlike most existing
methods, neither does this model assume a fixed functional
form for the MR signal attenuation (e.g. 2nd or 4th order
tensor) nor does it arbitrarily fix important mixture parameters like the number of components. We show that this continuous mixture has a closed form expression and leads to a
linear system which can be easily solved. Through extensive
experimentation with synthetic data we show that this technique outperforms various other state-of-the-art techniques
in resolving fiber crossings. Finally, we demonstrate the effectiveness of this method using real DW-MRI data from rat
brain and optic chiasm.</abstract>
	<selected></selected>
	<image>paper24.jpg</image>
	<type>c</type>
	<area>dti</area>
</article>
<article>
	<author>R. Kumar, A. Barmpoutis, A. Banerjee and B. C. Vemuri</author>
	<title>Face Relighting for Recognition</title>
	<journal>CISE Technical Report ID: REP-2008-451</journal>
	<urlvenue></urlvenue>
	<month></month>
	<volume></volume>
	<number></number>
	<year>2008</year>
	<pages>1-6</pages>
	<urlpdf>barmpoutis_tr08.pdf</urlpdf>
	<abstract>In this paper, we present a novel generative model for illumination of faces with cast shadows and specularities using a single example image. First, we present a novel method for the estimation of the ABRDF field of a face using B-spline modulated antisymmetric spherical harmonic functions which does not make the Lambertian assumption but yet uses only nine 2D images (which were shown in the literature to be the sufficient number of images for a convex Lambertian surface). Then, using information theoretic non-rigid registration and intensity mapping techniques, we propose a novel algorithm for transferring this field from one face to another using just one 2D image of the target face as input. We present photo-realistic results of synthesis of face images under novel illumination conditions (including extreme illumination) and demonstrate the effectiveness of the proposed framework in improving performance of various benchmark face recognition techniques on the Extended Yale B face database.</abstract>
	<selected></selected>
	<image>paper1.jpg</image>
	<type>t</type>
	<area>3dcv</area>
</article>
<article>
	<author>A. Barmpoutis, R. Kumar, B. C. Vemuri and A. Banerjee</author>
	<title>Beyond the Lambertian Assumption: A generative model for
Apparent BRDF fields of Faces using Anti-Symmetric Tensor Splines</title>
	<journal>In Proceedings of CVPR08: IEEE Conference on Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition</journal>
	<urlvenue>http://vision.eecs.ucf.edu/</urlvenue>
	<month>24 - 26 June</month>
	<volume></volume>
	<number></number>
	<year>2008</year>
	<pages>1-6</pages>
	<urlpdf>barmpoutis_cvpr08.pdf</urlpdf>
	<abstract>Human faces are neither exactly Lambertian nor entirely convex and
hence most models in literature which make the Lambertian assumption, fall
short when dealing with specularities and cast shadows. In this paper,
we present a novel anti-symmetric tensor spline (a spline for
tensor-valued functions) based method for the estimation of the
Apparent BRDF (ABRDF) field for human faces that seamlessly accounts
for specularities and cast shadows. Furthermore, unlike other
methods, it does not require any 3D information to build the model and
can work with as few as 9 images. In order to validate the accuracy of 
our anti-symmetric tensor spline model, we present a novel 
approximation of the ABRDF using a continuous mixture of single-lobed spherical functions.
We demonstrate the effectiveness of our anti-symmetric tensor-spline model in comparison
to other popular models in the literature, by presenting extensive results
for face relighting and face recognition using the Extended Yale B database.</abstract>
	<selected></selected>
	<image>paper23.jpg</image>
	<type>c</type>
	<area>3dcv</area>
</article>
<article>
	<author>A. Barmpoutis, B. C. Vemuri, D. Howland and J. R. Forder</author>
	<title>Extracting Tractosemas from a displacement
probability field for tractography in DW-MRI</title>
	<journal>In LNCS 5241, (Springer) Proceedings of MICCAI08: Int. Conf. on Medical Image Computing and Computer Assisted Intervention</journal>
	<urlvenue>http://miccai2008.rutgers.edu/</urlvenue>
	<month>6-10 September</month>
	<volume></volume>
	<number></number>
	<year>2008</year>
	<pages>9-16</pages>
	<urlpdf>barmpoutis_miccai08_lncs.pdf</urlpdf>
	<abstract>In this paper we present a novel method for estimating a
field of asymmetric spherical functions, dubbed tractosemas, given the
intra-voxel displacement probability information. The peaks of tractosemas
correspond to directions of distinct fibers, which can have either
symmetric or asymmetric local fiber structure. This is in contrast to the
existing methods that estimate fiber orientation distributions which are
naturally symmetric and therefore cannot model asymmetries such as
splaying fibers. We propose a method for extracting tractosemas from a
given field of displacement probability iso-surfaces via a diffusion process.
The diffusion is performed by minimizing a kernel convolution integral,
which leads to an update formula expressed in the convenient form of a
discrete kernel convolution. The kernel expresses the probability of diffusion
between two neighboring spherical functions and we model it by
the product of Gaussian and von-Mises distributions. The robustness of
our model in estimating accurate fiber orientations is validated via experiments
on synthetic and real diffusion-weighted magnetic resonance
(DW-MRI) datasets from an isolated rat hippocampus and a cats spinal
cord.</abstract>
	<selected></selected>
	<image>paper25.jpg</image>
	<type>c</type>
	<area></area>
</article>
<article>
	<author>A. Barmpoutis, B. C. Vemuri, D. Howland and J. R. Forder</author>
	<title>Groupwise non-rigid registration of 4th-order diffusion tensor fields and atlas construction</title>
	<journal>ISMRM09: Scientific Meeting of International Society for Magnetic Resonance in Medicine</journal>
	<urlvenue>http://www.ismrm.org/09/</urlvenue>
	<month>18-24 April</month>
	<volume></volume>
	<number></number>
	<year>2009</year>
	<pages></pages>
	<urlpdf></urlpdf>
	<abstract></abstract>
	<selected></selected>
	<image>paper1.jpg</image>
	<type>a</type>
	<area>dti</area>
</article>
<article>
	<author>E. Bozia, A. Barmpoutis, R. S. Wagman</author>
	<title>An Efficient Method for Digitizing Squeezes and Performing Automated Epigraphic Analysis.</title>
	<journal>140th Annual Meeting of the American Philological Association - American Institute of Archaeology</journal>
	<urlvenue>http://apaclassics.org/index.php/annual_meeting/past_annual_meetings/january_8-11_2009_140th_annual_meeting_philadelphia_pa/</urlvenue>
	<month>January 8-11</month>
	<volume></volume>
	<number></number>
	<year>2009</year>
	<pages></pages>
	<urlpdf></urlpdf>
	<abstract></abstract>
	<selected></selected>
	<image>paper1.jpg</image>
	<type>a</type>
	<area>dh</area>
</article>
<article>
	<author>A. Barmpoutis, E. Bozia, R. S. Wagman</author>
	<title>A novel framework for 3D reconstruction and analysis of ancient inscriptions</title>
	<journal>Journal of Machine Vision and Applications</journal>
	<urlvenue>http://www.springer.com/computer/computer+imaging/journal/138</urlvenue>
	<month></month>
	<volume>21</volume>
	<number>6</number>
	<year>2010</year>
	<pages>989-998</pages>
	<urlpdf>barmpoutis_mva10.pdf</urlpdf>
	<abstract>Studying ancient inscriptions is based up to date mostly on observation and manual analysis by means of 
which epigraphists attempt to establish a  geographical and chronological classification as well as to analyze the lettering techniques.
 In this paper we propose a novel  framework for efficient 3D reconstruction of inscriptions and for statistical analysis of their 
reconstructed surfaces. The  proposed framework employs a shape-from-shading technique to reconstruct in 3D the shape of the inscribed surfaces.
 The  obtained surfaces are segmented into smaller box-shaped regions containing single  letters.  These letters are classified into groups
 of same characters or symbols and then an atlas (average) letter shape is created for each character. For the construction of those atlases 
we  employ a functional minimization method that registers the surfaces of same letters to the unknown average surface, which is also estimated
 simultaneously. Using the estimated atlases an automated analysis of the inscribed  letters is performed. This framework can be effectively 
used for the study of the variations of the lettering techniques within an inscription or a set of  inscriptions. We applied our framework to 
five ancient Greek inscriptions. Our results are reported in detail and the variations found  in lettering techniques are commented on by 
archaeologists who also validate the accuracy of our proposed method.<br/><br/>A demo of this method can be found in: <a href="http://www.digitalepigraphy.org">www.digitalepigraphy.org</a></abstract>
	<selected></selected>
	<image>paper20.jpg</image>
	<type>j</type>
	<area>dh</area>
</article>
<article>
	<author>A. Barmpoutis and B. C. Vemuri</author>
	<title>Information theoretic methods for diffusion-weighted MRI analysis</title>
	<journal>In Emerging Trends in Visual Computing, F. Nielsen (ed.)</journal>
	<urlvenue>http://www.springer.com/computer/image+processing/book/978-3-642-00825-2</urlvenue>
	<month>Springer-Verlag, Heidelberg, Germany</month>
	<volume></volume>
	<number></number>
	<year>2009</year>
	<pages>327-346</pages>
	<urlpdf>info_theory.pdf</urlpdf>
	<abstract>Concepts from Information Theory have been used quite widely in Image
Processing, Computer Vision and Medical Image Analysis for several decades
now. Most widely used concepts are that of KL-divergence, minimum description
length (MDL), etc. These concepts have been popularly employed for image
registration, segmentation, classification etc. In this chapter we review several
methods, mostly developed by our group at the Center for Vision, Graphics &amp;
Medical Imaging in the University of Florida, that glean concepts from Information
Theory and apply them to achieve analysis of Diffusion-Weighted Magnetic
Resonance (DW-MRI) data.
This relatively new MRI modality allows one to non-invasively infer axonal
connectivity patterns in the central nervous system. The focus of this chapter is
to review automated image analysis techniques that allow us to automatically
segment the region of interest in the DWMRI image wherein one might want to
track the axonal pathways and also methods to reconstruct complex local tissue
geometries containing axonal fiber crossings. Implementation results illustrating
the algorithm application to real DW-MRI data sets are depicted to demonstrate
the effectiveness of the methods reviewed.</abstract>
	<selected></selected>
	<image>paper26.jpg</image>
	<type>bc</type>
	<area>dti</area>
</article>
<article>
	<author>R. Kumar, A. Barmpoutis, and B. C. Vemuri</author>
	<title>A physical basis for multi-fiber reconstruction from DW-MRI data</title>
	<journal>In Proceedings of ISBI09: IEEE International Symposium on Biomedical Imaging</journal>
	<urlvenue>http://www.biomedicalimaging.org</urlvenue>
	<month>June 28-July 1</month>
	<volume></volume>
	<number></number>
	<year>2009</year>
	<pages>626-629</pages>
	<urlpdf></urlpdf>
	<abstract>Recently various mathematical models have been proposed
to model the signal attenuation obtained from Diffusion
Weighted Magnetic Resonance Imaging (DW-MRI). Though
effective to various extents, almost all of the existing methods
involve model parameters which are abstract mathematical
quantities without any tangible connection to physical
quantities (e.g. the b-value, gradient pulse duration, pulse
separation etc.) involved in the DW-MRI acquisition process.
To address this disconnect, in this paper, we present
a multi-compartmental model which uses a physical model
for restricted diffusion in the cylindrical geometry as the constituent
basis function for multi-fiber reconstruction. Through
extensive experiments on synthetic data we establish the superiority
of the proposed method over the state-of-the-art
techniques in terms of fiber orientation detection accuracy.
We also present detailed results using human and rat brain
data and demonstrate that our method leads to meaningful
multi-fiber reconstruction even in the case of real data.</abstract>
	<selected></selected>
	<image>paper30.jpg</image>
	<type>c</type>
	<area>dti</area>
</article>
<article>
	<author>A. Barmpoutis, B. Jian, and B. C. Vemuri</author>
	<title>Adaptive kernels for multi-fiber reconstruction</title>
	<journal>In LNCS 5636 (Springer) Proceedings of IPMI09: Information Processing in Medical Imaging</journal>
	<urlvenue>http://www2.wiau.man.ac.uk/caws/Conferences/48/</urlvenue>
	<month>5-10 July</month>
	<volume></volume>
	<number></number>
	<year>2009</year>
	<pages>338-349</pages>
	<urlpdf>barmpoutis_ipmi09.pdf</urlpdf>
	<abstract>In this paper we present a novel method for multi-fiber 
reconstruction given a diffusion-weighted MRI dataset. There are several
existing methods that employ various spherical deconvolution kernels
for achieving this task. However the kernels in all of the existing methods rely on certain assumptions regarding the properties of the 
underlying fibers, which introduce inaccuracies and unnatural limitations in
them. Our model is a non trivial generalization of the spherical deconvolution model, which unlike the existing methods does not make use
of a fix-shaped kernel. Instead, the shape of the kernel is estimated simultaneously with the rest of the unknown parameters by employing a
general adaptive model that can theoretically approximate any spherical deconvolution kernel. The performance of our model is demonstrated
using simulated and real diffusion-weighed MR datasets and compared
quantitatively with several existing techniques in literature. The results
obtained indicate that our model has superior performance that is close
to the theoretic limit of the best possible achievable result.</abstract>
	<selected></selected>
	<image>paper29.jpg</image>
	<type>c</type>
	<area>dti</area>
</article>
<article>
	<author>A. Barmpoutis, and B. C. Vemuri</author>
	<title>Groupwise Registration and atlas construction of 4th-order tensor fields using the R+ Riemannian metric</title>
	<journal>In LNCS 5761 (Springer) Proceedings of MICCAI09: Int. Conf. on Medical Image Computing and Computer Assisted Intervention</journal>
	<urlvenue>http://www.miccai2009.org/</urlvenue>
	<month>22-24 September</month>
	<volume></volume>
	<number></number>
	<year>2009</year>
	<pages>640-647</pages>
	<urlpdf>barmpoutis_miccai09.pdf</urlpdf>
	<abstract>Registration of Diffusion-Weighted MR Images (DW-MRI) can be achieved by registering the corresponding 2nd-order
 Diffusion Tensor Images (DTI). However, it has been shown that higher-order diffusion tensors (e.g. order-4) outperform the traditional DTI 
in approximating complex fiber structures such as fiber crossings. In this paper we present a novel method for unbiased group-wise non-rigid 
registration and atlas construction of 4th-order diffusion tensor fields. To the best of our knowledge there is no other existing method to 
achieve this task. First we define a metric on the space of positive-valued functions based on the Riemannian metric of real positive numbers 
(denoted by R+). Then, we use this metric in a novel functional minimization method for non-rigid 4th-order tensor field registration. We 
define a cost function that accounts for the 4th-order tensor re-orientation during the registration process and has analytic derivatives 
with respect to the transformation parameters. Finally, the tensor field atlas is computed as the minimizer of the variance defined using the 
Riemannian metric. We quantitatively compare the proposed method with other techniques that register scalar-valued or diffusion tensor (rank-2) 
representations of the DWMRI. This comparison is achieved using synthetic data and atlas construction results are depicted for real human 
hippocampal data sets.</abstract>
	<selected></selected>
	<image>paper19.jpg</image>
	<type>c</type>
	<area>dti</area>
</article>
<article>
	<author>R. Kumar, A. Barmpoutis, A. Banerjee, B. C. Vemuri</author>
	<title>Non-Lambertian Reflectance Modeling and Shape Recovery for Faces using Anti-Symmetric Tensor Splines</title>
	<journal>IEEE Transactions on Pattern Analysis and Machine Intelligence</journal>
	<urlvenue>www.computer.org/tpami/</urlvenue>
	<month></month>
	<volume>33</volume>
	<number>3</number>
	<year>2011</year>
	<pages>533-567</pages>
	<urlpdf>tensor_splines_pami.pdf</urlpdf>
	<abstract>Modeling illumination effects and pose variations of a face is of fundamental importance in the field of facial image analysis.
Most of the conventional techniques that simultaneously address both of these problems work with the Lambertian assumption and
thus, fall short of accurately capturing the complex intensity variation that the facial images exhibit or recovering their 3D shape in
presence of specularities and cast shadows. In this paper we present a novel anti-symmetric tensor spline based framework for
facial image analysis. We show that using this framework, facial apparent BRDF field can be accurately estimated while seamlessly
accounting for cast shadows and specularities. Further, using local neighborhood information, the same framework can be exploited to
recover the 3D shape of the face (to handle pose variation). We quantitatively validate the accuracy of the anti-symmetric tensor spline
model using a more general continuous mixture of single lobed spherical functions. We demonstrate the effectiveness of our technique
by presenting extensive experimental results for face relighting, 3D shape recovery and face recognition using the Extended Yale B and
CMU PIE benchmark datasets.</abstract>
	<selected></selected>
	<image>paper28.jpg</image>
	<type>j</type>
	<area>3dcv</area>
</article>
<article>
	<author>A. Barmpoutis, M. S. Hwang, D. Howland, J. R. Forder and B. C. Vemuri</author>
	<title>Regularized Positive-Definite Fourth-Order Tensor Field Estimation from DW-MRI</title>
	<journal>NeuroImage</journal>
	<urlvenue>http://www.elsevier.com/locate/ynimg</urlvenue>
	<month>March</month>
	<volume>45</volume>
	<number>1 sup.1</number>
	<year>2009</year>
	<pages>153-162</pages>
	<urlpdf>barmpoutis_ni09.pdf</urlpdf>
	<abstract>In Diffusion Weighted Magnetic Resonance Image (DW-MRI) processing,
a 2nd order tensor has been commonly used to approximate the
diffusivity function at each lattice point of the DW-MRI data. From
this tensor approximation, one can compute useful scalar quantities
(e.g. anisotropy, mean diffusivity) which have been clinically used
for monitoring encephalopathy, sclerosis, ischemia and other brain
disorders. It is now well known that this 2nd-order tensor
approximation fails to capture complex local tissue structures, e.g.
crossing fibers, and as a result the scalar quantities derived from
these tensors are grossly inaccurate at such locations. In this
paper we employ a 4th order symmetric positive-definite (SPD)
tensor approximation to represent the diffusivity function and
present a novel technique to estimate these tensors from the DW-MRI
data guaranteeing the SPD property. Several articles have been
reported in literature on higher order tensor approximations of the
diffusivity function but none of them guarantee the positivity of
the estimates, which is a fundamental constraint since negative
values of the diffusivity are not meaningful. In this paper we
represent the 4th-order tensors as ternary quartics and then
apply Hilbert's theorem on ternary quartics along with the Iwasawa
parametrization to guarantee an SPD 4th-order tensor
approximation from the DW-MRI data. The performance of this model is
depicted on synthetic data as well as real DW-MRIs from a set of excised control and injured rat spinal cords,
showing accurate estimation of scalar quantities such as generalized
anisotropy and trace as well as fiber orientations.</abstract>
	<selected></selected>
	<image>paper27.jpg</image>
	<type>j</type>
	<area>dti</area>
</article>
<article>
	<author>Y. T. Weldeselassie, A. Barmpoutis and S. Atkins</author>
	<title>Symmetric Positive-Definite Cartesian Tensor Orientation Distribution Functions (CT-ODF)</title>
	<journal>In LNCS 6361 (Springer) Proceedings of MICCAI10: Int. Conf. on Medical Image Computing and Computer Assisted Intervention</journal>
	<urlvenue>http://www.miccai2010.org</urlvenue>
	<month>20-24 September</month>
	<volume></volume>
	<number></number>
	<year>2010</year>
	<pages>582-589</pages>
	<urlpdf>barmpoutis_miccai10.pdf</urlpdf>
	<abstract>In this paper we present a novel method for estimating a field
of orientation distribution functions (ODF) from a given set of Diffusion-
Weighted MR images. In our technique the ODF is modeled by Cartesian
tensor basis using a parametrization that explicitly enforces the positive
definite property to the computed ODFs. The computed Cartesian tensors,
dubbed Cartesian Tensor-ODFs (CT-ODFs), are symmetric positive
definite tensors whose coefficients can be efficiently estimated by
solving a linear system with non-negative constraints. Furthermore, we
show how to use our method for converting higher-order diffusion tensors
to CT-ODFs, which is an essential task since the maxima of higher-order
tensors do not correspond to the underlying fiber orientations. We quantitatively
evaluate our method using simulated DW-MR images as well
as a real brain dataset from a post-mortem porcine brain. The results
conclusively demonstrate the superiority of the proposed technique over
several existing multi-fiber reconstruction methods.</abstract>
	<selected></selected>
	<image>paper35.jpg</image>
	<type>c</type>
	<area>dti</area>
</article>
<article>
	<author>A. Barmpoutis and B. C. Vemuri</author>
	<title>A unified framework for estimating diffusion tensors of any order
with symmetric positive-definite constraints</title>
	<journal>In Proceedings of ISBI10: IEEE International Symposium on Biomedical Imaging</journal>
	<urlvenue>http://www.biomedicalimaging.org</urlvenue>
	<month>14-17 April</month>
	<volume></volume>
	<number></number>
	<year>2010</year>
	<pages>1385-1388</pages>
	<urlpdf>barmpoutis_isbi10.pdf</urlpdf>
	<abstract>Cartesian tensors of various orders have been employed for
either modeling the diffusivity or the orientation distribution
function in Diffusion-Weighted MRI datasets. In both cases,
the estimated tensors have to be positive-definite since they
model positive-valued functions. In this paper we present a
novel unified framework for estimating positive-definite tensors
of any order, in contrast to the existing methods in literature,
which are either order-specific or fail to handle the
positive-definite property. The proposed framework employs
a homogeneous polynomial parametrization that covers the
full space of any order positive-definite tensors and explicitly
imposes the positive-definite constraint on the estimated tensors.
We show that this parametrization leads to a linear system
that is solved using the non-negative least squares technique.
The framework is demonstrated using synthetic and
real data from an excised rat hippocampus.</abstract>
	<selected></selected>
	<image>paper34.jpg</image>
	<type>c</type>
	<area>dti</area>
</article>
<article>
	<author>A. Barmpoutis and J. Zhuo</author>
	<title>Diffusion Kurtosis Imaging: Robust Estimation from DW-MRI using Homogeneous Polynomials</title>
	<journal>In Proceedings of ISBI11: IEEE International Symposium on Biomedical Imaging</journal>
	<urlvenue>http://www.biomedicalimaging.org</urlvenue>
	<month>30 March-2 April</month>
	<volume></volume>
	<number></number>
	<year>2011</year>
	<pages>262-265</pages>
	<urlpdf>barmpoutis_isbi11.pdf</urlpdf>
	<abstract>Several tensor-based models have been presented in literature
for parameterizing the water diffusion in Diffusion-Weighted
MRI datasets, namely Diffusion Tensor Imaging (DTI), Generalized
Tensor Imaging (GTI), and Diffusion Kurtosis Imaging
(DKI). In this paper we use homogeneous trivariate polynomials
to show that GTI is a special case of DKI for single
angular shell acquisitions, and then we employ the theory for
imposing positive semi-definite (PSD) constraints to GTIs in
order to performrobust estimation of the DKI parameters. We
propose a novel framework for DKI estimation that simultaneously
imposes constraints to the diffusivity function, diffusion
tensor and diffusion kurtosis. These three constraints are
parameterized explicitly as a set of linear systems that can be
efficiently solved using the non-negative least squares technique.
The robustness of our framework is demonstrated using
synthetic and real data from a human brain.</abstract>
	<selected></selected>
	<image>paper36.jpg</image>
	<type>c</type>
	<area>dti</area>
</article>
<article>
	<author>S. Ray, W. ODell, A. Barmpoutis</author>
	<title>Perpendicular Fiber Tracking for Fiber Bundle Analysis</title>
	<journal>1st International Conference on Computational Biomedicine</journal>
	<urlvenue></urlvenue>
	<month>February 29 - March 2</month>
	<volume></volume>
	<number></number>
	<year>2012</year>
	<pages></pages>
	<urlpdf></urlpdf>
	<abstract></abstract>
	<selected></selected>
	<image>paper38.jpg</image>
	<type>a</type>
	<area>dti</area>
</article>
<article>
	<author>E. Bozia, A. Barmpoutis,  and R. S. Wagman</author>
	<title>The First Online 3D Epigraphic Library</title>
	<journal>In Proceedings of CIEGL12: 14th International Congress of Greek and Latin Epigraphy, Humboldt University, Berlin</journal>
	<urlvenue>http://www.congressus2012.de/</urlvenue>
	<month>27 - 31 Aug</month>
	<volume></volume>
	<number></number>
	<year>2012</year>
	<pages></pages>
	<urlpdf>barmpoutis_ciegl12.pdf</urlpdf>
	<abstract>In our presentation we intend to introduce the Digital Epigraphy Toolbox which is a crossplatform web-application designed to facilitate the digital preservation, study, and electronic 
dissemination of ancient inscriptions1. It allows epigraphists to digitize in 3D their epigraphic 
squeezes using our novel cost-effective technique, which overcomes the limitations of the 
current methods for digitizing epigraphic data in 2-dimensions only. Our toolbox contains 
several options for 3D visualization of inscriptions, as well as a set of scientific tools for 
analyzing the lettering techniques and performing quantitative analysis of the letterform 
variations. Furthermore, the users have the option to share their data, as well as search 
other uploaded collections of 3D inscriptions in a semi-supervised dynamic library. This 
dynamic library is organized thematically according to language, area of origin, and date and 
contains a comprehensive record of the inscription in the form of plain text, 3D model, 2D 
photographs, and other epigraphic information.</abstract>
	<selected></selected>
	<image>paper40.jpg</image>
	<type>a</type>
	<area>dh</area>
</article>
<article>
	<author>A. Barmpoutis</author>
	<title>A novel Augmented-Reality Educational System for Classical Drama 
using RGB-D</title>
	<journal>10th Annual Meeting, International Digital Media and Arts Association</journal>
	<urlvenue>http://www.idmaa.org/</urlvenue>
	<month>November 8-10</month>
	<volume></volume>
	<number></number>
	<year>2012</year>
	<pages></pages>
	<urlpdf></urlpdf>
	<abstract>Depth cameras have been used widely as low-cost computer peripheral devices for various applications related to virtual-reality interaction by tracking and utilizing the natural motion of the users. The acquired depth information can be mapped to RGB video data, producing a sequence of 3D video frames (known as RGB-D) that can be used in mixed- or augmented-reality applications. 
In this paper a novel system is presented for facilitating the study of classical drama and potentially other forms of literature in which the spatiotemporal interactions of the portrayed characters play significant role in the study of the original text. In the particular case of classical Greek and Roman drama there is evidence regarding the number of actors and dancers (chorus), their gender restrictions, the theater in which it was originally performed, the structure of the theater (type, size, auxiliary rooms available, etc.), as well as information about costumes and mechanical devices used during the performances. Questions such as "how many dancers in circular arrangement can fit on the stage of the theater of Dionysus in Athens?", "what are the possible arrangements of the chorus on a rectangular stage?", "how much time does it take to walk from the center of the stage to the back stage in the theater of Epidaurus?", "what would be the appropriate size of props, costume accessories, and other machinery so as to be visible to everyone in the audience, including people in the back rows?" cannot be easily answered by the traditional teaching methodologies in the humanities. The proposed system offers a novel tool in the area of digital humanities that helps students and researchers answer such questions and understand the circumstances of performance and ultimately interpret the text through an experiential learning environment.
</abstract>
	<selected></selected>
	<image>paper39.jpg</image>
	<type>a</type>
	<area>dh</area>
</article>
<article>
	<author>Y. Weldeselassie, A. Barmpoutis and S. Atkins</author>
	<title>Symmetric positive-definite Cartesian tensor fiber orientation distributions (CT-FOD)</title>
	<journal>Medical Image Analysis</journal>
	<urlvenue>http://www.journals.elsevier.com/medical-image-analysis/</urlvenue>
	<month>August</month>
	<volume>16</volume>
	<number>6</number>
	<year>2012</year>
	<pages>1121-1129</pages>
	<urlpdf>barmpoutis_mia12.pdf</urlpdf>
	<abstract>A novel method for estimating a field of fiber orientation distribution (FOD) based on signal de-convolution from a given set of diffusion weighted magnetic resonance (DW-MR) images is presented. We model the FOD by higher order Cartesian tensor basis using a parametrization that explicitly enforces the positive semi-definite property to the computed FOD. The computed Cartesian tensors, dubbed Cartesian Tensor-FOD (CT-FOD), are symmetric positive semi-definite tensors whose coefficients can be efficiently estimated by solving a linear system with non-negative constraints. Next, we show how to use our method for converting higher-order diffusion tensors to CT-FODs, which is an essential task since the maxima of higher-order tensors do not correspond to the underlying fiber orientations. Finally, we propose a diffusion anisotropy index computed directly from CT-FODs using higher order tensor distance measures thus consolidating the whole analysis pipeline of diffusion imaging solely using CT-FODs. We evaluate our method qualitatively and quantitatively using simulated DW-MR images, phantom images, and human brain real dataset. The results conclusively demonstrate the superiority of the proposed technique over several existing multifiber reconstruction methods.</abstract>
	<selected></selected>
	<image>paper35.jpg</image>
	<type>j</type>
	<area>dti</area>
</article>
<article>
	<author>A. Barmpoutis, J. Ho and B. C. Vemuri</author>
	<title>Approximating symmetric positive semi-definite tensors of even order</title>
	<journal>SIAM Journal on Imaging Sciences</journal>
	<urlvenue>http://www.siam.org/journals/siims.php</urlvenue>
	<month></month>
	<volume>5</volume>
	<number>1</number>
	<year>2012</year>
	<pages>434-464</pages>
	<urlpdf>barmpoutis_siims12.pdf</urlpdf>
	<abstract>Tensors of various orders can be used for modeling physical quantities such as strain and diffusion as well as curvature and other quantities of geometric origin. Depending on the physical properties of the modeled quantity, the estimated tensors are often required to satisfy the positivity constraint, which can be satisfied only with tensors of even order. Although the space P^2m_0 of 2m^th-
order symmetric positive semi-definite tensors is known to be a convex cone, enforcing positivity
constraint directly on P^2m_0 is usually not straightforward computationally because there is no known
analytic description of P^2m_0 for m &gt; 1. In this paper, we propose a novel approach for enforcing the
positivity constraint on even-order tensors by approximating the cone P^2m_0 for the cases 0 &lt; m &lt; 3,
and presenting an explicit characterization of the approximation Sigma_2m &lt; Omega_2m for m &gt;= 1, using
the subset Omega_2m &lt; P^2m_0 of semi-definite tensors that can be written as a sum of squares of tensors
of order m. Furthermore, we show that this approximation leads to a non-negative linear leastsquares
(NNLS) optimization problem with the complexity that equals the number of generators in
Sigma_2m. Finally, we experimentally validate the proposed approach and we present an application for
computing 2mth-order diffusion tensors from Diffusion Weighted Magnetic Resonance Images.</abstract>
	<selected></selected>
	<image>paper34.jpg</image>
	<type>j</type>
	<area>dti</area>
</article>
<article>
	<author>S. Ray, W. ODell, A. Barmpoutis</author>
	<title>Estimation of Fiber Bundle Sections for Interactive Fiber Analysis</title>
	<journal>26th International Congress on Computer Assisted Radiology and Surgery, Int. J. CARS</journal>
	<urlvenue>http://www.cars-int.org/</urlvenue>
	<month>27-30 June</month>
	<volume>6</volume>
	<number>Suppl. 1</number>
	<year>2012</year>
	<pages>S31-S35</pages>
	<urlpdf>barmpoutis_cars12.pdf</urlpdf>
	<abstract>During the last decade the area of Diffusion Weighted MRI analysis
has gained significant scientific attention and many techniques have
been introduced for analyzing the diffusivity patterns in neural tissues
and visualizing the neural fiber tracts. However, the majority of these
methods have not been adopted for clinical use due to various reasons,
including the computational demands as well as the large complexity
of the analyzed neural fiber tracking information. In this paper we
present an interactive algorithm for fiber bundle analysis that computes
in real time statistics on the variation of the structure, size, and
curvature along a fiber bundle. The proposed fiber metrics can be used
as markers for diagnosing and monitoring atrophy for epilepsy,
schizophrenia, depression, hypoxia-ischemia, trauma, Alzheimers
disease, and other dementias.</abstract>
	<selected></selected>
	<image>paper38.jpg</image>
	<type>c</type>
	<area>dti</area>
</article>
<article>
	<author>A. Barmpoutis</author>
	<title>Automated Human Avatar Synthesis for Obesity Control using Low-Cost Depth Cameras</title>
	<journal>20th MMVR Conference: Medicine Meets Virtual Reality</journal>
	<urlvenue>http://www.nextmed.com/</urlvenue>
	<month>20-23 February</month>
	<volume></volume>
	<number></number>
	<year>2013</year>
	<pages></pages>
	<urlpdf>barmpoutis_mmvr13.pdf</urlpdf>
	<abstract>In this paper a framework is presented for monitoring shape changes on the human body with applications to obesity control. This framework uses a lowcost infrared depth camera in order to capture the 3D shape of the human body and approximate it as a set of spherical functions.</abstract>
	<selected></selected>
	<image>paper37.jpg</image>
	<type>c</type>
	<area>3dcv</area>
</article>
<article>
	<author>E. Bozia, A. Barmpoutis, and R. S. Wagman</author>
	<title>Open-Access Epigraphy: Electronic Dissemination of 3D digitized Archaeological Material</title>
	<journal>In Proceedings of the International Conference on Information Technologies for Epigraphy and Digital Cultural Heritage in the Ancient World (EAGLE 2014)</journal>
	<urlvenue>http://www.eagle-network.eu/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/Paris-Conference-Proceedings.pdf</urlvenue>
	<month>29-30 September and 1 October</month>
	<volume></volume>
	<number></number>
	<year>2014</year>
	<pages>421-435</pages>
	<urlpdf>barmpoutis_eagle14.pdf</urlpdf>
	<abstract>Preservation and dissemination of archaeological material has always been an issue of concern for the academic research community. On the one hand, the fragility of the material limits their study. On the other hand, such material is housed in museums, libraries, and institutions worldwide, something that significantly thwarts their accessibility. Technology, high resolution 2D pictures, and electronic databases have attempted to overcome the aforementioned limitations. However, lack of contact with the physical object as a tridimensional structure still significantly obstructs research. In this paper we present the latest advances of the Digital Epigraphy Toolbox, a novel project that focuses on the digitization in 3D of ancient inscriptions from ektypa, the multi-modal visualization of their 3D models, the facilitation of interlinked 3D digitized records, and the easy and effective electronic dissemination of archaeological material. This project offers options for cost-effective shape-from-shading 3D digitization of ektypa, using a flatbed scanner, and various visualization modes, such as photorealistic 3D views and informative fingerprint map and depth map that assist scholars understand the structural characteristics of the artifacts. Finally, the project facilitates the dissemination of the 3D digitized objects by providing the users with an embeddable 3D viewer which can be easily imported in third-party databases, collections, and personal websites.</abstract>
	<selected></selected>
	<image>paper40.jpg</image>
	<type>c</type>
	<area>dh</area>
</article>
<article>
	<author>S. Ray, W. ODell, and A. Barmpoutis</author>
	<title>Perpendicular Fiber Tracking for Neural Fiber Bundle Analysis using Diffusion MRI</title>
	<journal>International Journal of Bioinformatics and Research Applications, Special Issue on Computational Biomedicine</journal>
	<urlvenue>http://www.inderscience.com/jhome.php?jcode=ijbra</urlvenue>
	<month>January</month>
	<volume>10</volume>
	<number>1</number>
	<year>2014</year>
	<pages>75-92</pages>
	<urlpdf>barmpoutis_ijbra.pdf</urlpdf>
	<abstract>Information on the directionality and structure of axonal fibers in neural tissue can be obtained by analyzing Diffusion-Weighted MRI datasets. Several fiber tracking algorithms have been presented in literature that trace the underlying field of principal orientations of water diffusion, which correspond to the local primary eigenvectors of the diffusion tensor field. However, the majority of the existing techniques ignore the secondary and tertiary orientations of diffusion, which contain significant information on the local patterns of diffusion. In this paper we introduce the idea of perpendicular fiber tracking and we present a novel dynamic programming method that traces surfaces, which are locally perpendicular to the axonal fibers. This is achieved by using a cost function, with geometric and fiber orientation constraints, that is evaluated dynamically for every voxel in the image domain starting from a given seed point. The proposed method is tested using synthetic and real DW-MRI datasets. The results conclusively demonstrate the accuracy and effectiveness of our method.</abstract>
	<selected></selected>
	<image>paper38.jpg</image>
	<type>j</type>
	<area>dti</area>
</article>
<article>
	<author>A. Barmpoutis</author>
	<title>Automated Human Avatar Synthesis for Obesity Control using Low-Cost Depth Cameras</title>
	<journal>Studies in Health Technology and Informatics, IOS press</journal>
	<urlvenue>http://www.iospress.nl/bookserie/studies-in-health-technology-and-informatics/</urlvenue>
	<month>February</month>
	<volume>184</volume>
	<number></number>
	<year>2013</year>
	<pages>36-42</pages>
	<urlpdf>barmpoutis_mmvr13.pdf</urlpdf>
	<abstract>In this paper a framework is presented for monitoring shape changes on the human body with applications to obesity control. This framework uses a lowcost infrared depth camera in order to capture the 3D shape of the human body and approximate it as a set of spherical functions.</abstract>
	<selected></selected>
	<image>paper37.jpg</image>
	<type>j</type>
	<area>3dcv</area>
</article>
<article>
	<author>A. Kondyli, V. Sisiopiku, and A. Barmpoutis</author>
	<title>A 3D experimental framework for exploring drivers' body activity using infrared depth sensors</title>
	<journal>IEEE International Conference on Connected Vehicles</journal>
	<urlvenue>http://www.ieeeexplore.com/xpl/mostRecentIssue.jsp?punumber=6784566</urlvenue>
	<month>2-6 December</month>
	<volume></volume>
	<number></number>
	<year>2013</year>
	<pages>574-579</pages>
	<urlpdf>barmpoutis_iccve13.pdf</urlpdf>
	<abstract>A significant amount of research has been involved with the development of advanced driver-assistance systems. Such systems typically include radars, laser or video sensors that detect the vehicle trajectory and warn for an imminent lane departure, or sense the front vehicle's speed and apply the brakes of the following vehicle to maintain safe distance headways (i.e., collision avoidance system). However, most of these systems rely on the subject vehicle and surrounding vehicles' position and do not explicitly consider the driver's actions during the driving task. In addition safety research has focused on eye tracking as a means of capturing driver's attention, fatigue, or drowsiness; however, the body posture has not been investigated in depth. This paper presents a novel approach for studying the actual movements of drivers inside the vehicle, when performing specific maneuver types such as lane changing and merging. This information can be useful for identifying specific body movements that may hide potentially unsafe situations. A pilot study was conducted along a freeway and arterial segment, where the 3D shapes of selected participants were constructed with the use of a low-cost infrared depth sensor (Microsoft Kinect) while merging and changing lanes. The analysis of the 3D shapes shows that there are important differences between participants when performing similar driving maneuvers. The preliminary results of this pilot research set the basis for implementing the proposed methodological framework for conducting full-scale experiments with a variety of participants, and exploring differences due to driver behavior attributes, such as age, gender and driving experience.</abstract>
	<selected></selected>
	<image>paper41.jpg</image>
	<type>c</type>
	<area>3dcv</area>
</article>
<article>
	<author>A. Barmpoutis</author>
	<title>Tensor Body: Real-time Reconstruction of the Human Body and Avatar Synthesis from RGB-D</title>
	<journal>IEEE Transactions on Cybernetics, Special issue on Computer Vision for RGB-D Sensors: Kinect and Its Applications</journal>
	<urlvenue>http://ieeexplore.ieee.org/xpl/articleDetails.jsp?arnumber=6583279</urlvenue>
	<month>October</month>
	<volume>43</volume>
	<number>5</number>
	<year>2013</year>
	<pages>1347-1356</pages>
	<urlpdf>barmpoutis_ieeetc13.pdf</urlpdf>
	<abstract>Real-time 3D reconstruction of the human body has many applications in anthropometry, telecommunications,
gaming, fashion, and other areas of human-computer interaction. In this paper a novel framework is presented for reconstructing
the 3D model of the human body from a sequence of RGBD frames. The reconstruction is performed in real time while
the human subject moves arbitrarily in front of the camera. The method employs a novel parameterization of cylindrical-type
objects using Cartesian tensor and b-spline bases along the radial and longitudinal dimension respectively. The proposed model,
dubbed tensor body, is fitted to the input data using a multistep framework that involves segmentation of the different body
regions, robust filtering of the data via a dynamic histogram, and energy-based optimization with positive-definite constraints.
A Riemannian metric on the space of positive-definite tensor splines is analytically defined and employed in this framework.
The efficacy of the presented methods is demonstrated in several real-data experiments using the Microsoft Kinect sensor.</abstract>
	<selected></selected>
	<image>paper33.jpg</image>
	<type>j</type>
	<area>3dcv</area>
</article>
<article>
	<author>E.J. Fox, S. Flynn, A. Barmpoutis, D.R. Howland, A.L. Behrman</author>
	<title>Exciting kids to walk: Enhancing walking recovery through game technology.</title>
	<journal>8th Annual Games for Health Conference</journal>
	<urlvenue>http://gamesforhealth.org/conferences/conf-2012/</urlvenue>
	<month>12-14 June</month>
	<volume></volume>
	<number></number>
	<year>2012</year>
	<pages></pages>
	<urlpdf></urlpdf>
	<abstract>Children with neurological injuries, including spinal cord injury and cerebral palsy, experience devastating effects that are endured across their lifespans.  Traditional rehabilitation interventions to improve upright mobility use bracing and assistive devices to compensate for lost function.  In contrast, locomotor training promotes recovery by activating the neuromuscular system and promoting activity-dependent plasticity without compensatory devices.  Locomotor training optimizes task-specific sensory input during intense stepping practice. This rehabilitation approach is beneficial for adults with spinal cord injuries and is a promising recovery-based approach for children with neurological injuries.  During locomotor training, stepping and standing often are practised on a treadmill for over an hour causing many children to lose motivation and become bored. As attention and focus wane,critical task-specific movements, such as upright trunk posture and reciprocal arm swing,become near impossible to evoke.  Most importantly, a less intense and effective training session compromises the child's recovery.<br/><br/>
Incorporation of interactive and engaging video games is an innovative approach to enhance rehabilitation.  Games motivate children and promote practice and performance of specific motor skills.  Although commercial games have demonstrated therapeutic effects when applied to children with neurological injuries, most games do not consider the specific impairments that are common in children with cerebral palsy and SCI and are not designed for use during locomotor training. Therefore,our long-term objective is to design and develop an engaging and interactive game that enhances locomotor training for children with neurological injuries.  This project is the first phase in meeting this objective and will result in the development of a technical game prototype. We will use the transdisciplinary game design approach developed by Blue Marble that incorporates expertise from a variety of professions, with input from end-users at each stage of development. Our collaborative multidisciplinary team consists of experts in basic neuroscience, rehabilitation, computer science, programming, art, and game design. We will use focus group methodology to obtain initial design input from children with cerebral palsy and spinal cord injuries, their caregivers, and clinicians. Intermediate and final game designs will be evaluated by children, caregivers and clinicians. A top priority will be a design that is optimal for use with locomotor training.<br/><br/>
We will use the PrimeSense camera and the Unity 3D game development tool to develop a fun, interactive game that uses human gestures as a key element for game control. The goal is to engage children to maintain an upright trunk posture and perform walking-related movements with their arms and legs in order to play the game.  Quantitative data pertaining to the child's movements will be recorded during the use of the game to further optimize the game parameters and evaluate the child's movements during the locomotor training session.  Overall these game features will excite and engage children to perform task-specific movements, increase time on task, and make locomotor training more exciting and fun, thus 'Exciting Kids to Walk'.   
</abstract>
	<selected></selected>
	<image>paper43.jpg</image>
	<type>a</type>
	<area>other</area>
</article>
<article>
	<author>E.J. Fox, S. Flynn, A. Barmpoutis, D.R. Howland, A.L. Behrman</author>
	<title>Exciting kids to walk: Game technology to enhance locomotor training in children with spinal cord injury.</title>
	<journal>Howard H. Steel Conference-Pediatric Spinal Cord Injuries and Dysfunction. Lake Buena Vista, FL</journal>
	<urlvenue>http://www.pedssci.com/meetings/2012/howardsteel/program.aspx</urlvenue>
	<month>29 November - 1 December</month>
	<volume></volume>
	<number></number>
	<year>2012</year>
	<pages></pages>
	<urlpdf></urlpdf>
	<abstract>Locomotor training is a rehabilitation intervention that aims to promote recovery of walking, by activating the neuromuscular system below the level of the spinal cord lesion.  Locomotor training optimizes task-specific sensory input during intense stepping practice to promote activity-dependent plasticity. This rehabilitation approach is beneficial for adults with spinal cord injuries and is a promising rehabilitation approach for children with incomplete spinal cord injuries.  During locomotor training, stepping and standing often are practiced on a treadmill for over an hour causing many children to lose motivation and become bored. As attention and focus wane, critical task-specific movements, such as upright trunk posture and reciprocal arm swing, become near impossible to evoke.  Most importantly, a less intense and effective training session compromises the child's recovery.<br/><br/>  
Incorporation of interactive and engaging video games is an innovative approach to enhance rehabilitation.  Games motivate children and promote practice and performance of specific motor skills.  Although commercial games have demonstrated therapeutic effects when applied to children with neurological injuries, most games do not consider the specific impairments that are common in children with spinal cord injury and are not designed for use during locomotor training.   Therefore, our long-term objective is to design and develop an engaging and interactive game that enhances locomotor training for children with neurological injuries.  This project is the first phase in meeting this objective and will result in the development of a technical game prototype. We are applying a trans-disciplinary game design approach that incorporates expertise from a variety of professions, with input from end-users at each stage of development. Our multidisciplinary team consists of experts in basic neuroscience, rehabilitation, computer science, programming, art, and game design. We have conducted interviews and focus groups to obtain initial game-design input from children with spinal cord injuries, their caregivers, and clinicians. Intermediate and final game designs will be evaluated by children, caregivers and clinicians. A top priority will be a design that is optimal for use with locomotor training.<br/><br/>
We are using the Microsoft Kinect camera to develop a fun, interactive game that uses human gestures as a key element for game control. Our goal is to engage children to maintain an upright trunk posture and perform walking-related movements with their arms and legs in order to play the game.  To accomplish this, we are applying custom-written software to detect and track movement in the unique locomotor training treadmill environment.  Quantitative data pertaining to the child's movements will be recorded during the use of the game to further optimize the game parameters and evaluate the child's movements during the locomotor training session.  Overall these game features will excite and engage children to perform task-specific movements, increase time on task, and make locomotor training more exciting and fun, thus 'Exciting Kids to Walk'.   This work is supported in part by the NIH/NCATS Clinical and Translational Science Award to the University of Florida UL1 TR000064.   
</abstract>
	<selected></selected>
	<image>paper43.jpg</image>
	<type>a</type>
	<area>other</area>
</article>
<article>
	<author>E.J. Fox, S. Flynn, A. Barmpoutis, S. Trimble, D.R. Howland, A.L. Behrman</author>
	<title>Game technology to enhance locomotor training in children with neurological injuries.</title>
	<journal>American Physical Therapy Association, Combined Sections Meeting, San Diego, CA</journal>
	<urlvenue>http://www.apta.org/csm/</urlvenue>
	<month>21-24 January</month>
	<volume></volume>
	<number></number>
	<year>2013</year>
	<pages></pages>
	<urlpdf></urlpdf>
	<abstract>Locomotor training is a rehabilitation approach that optimizes task-specific sensory input during intense 
stepping practice. This approach is beneficial for adults with spinal cord injuries and is a promising intervention 
for children with neurological injuries. During locomotor training stepping and standing often are practiced for 
over an hour causing many children to lose motivation and become bored. As attention and focus wane, critical 
task-specific movements, such as upright trunk posture and reciprocal arm swing, become nearly impossible to 
evoke. Most importantly, these less intense and effective training sessions may compromise a child's recovery. 
Incorporation of interactive and engaging video games is an innovative approach to enhance rehabilitation. 
Although commercial games have demonstrated therapeutic effects when applied to children with neurological 
injuries, most games do not consider the specific impairments that are common in children with neurological 
injuries and are not designed for use during locomotor training. We are therefore, developing an interactive 
video game, designed to enhance locomotor training in children with neurological injuries. <br/><br/>
 We have assembled a multidisciplinary team with experts in neuroscience, rehabilitation, computer 
science, and video game design. We are using existing, affordable technologies to develop a game that is not 
only interactive and motivating to children, but that also is based on key determinants of walking control. 
Specifically, the video game will be controlled by critical features of locomotor training, which are based on the 
neural control of walking. These features, such as trunk posture, reciprocal arm swing, and stepping can be 
recorded during the use of the game to optimize the parameters of the game and to collect valuable data about 
the patient's rehabilitation session. </abstract>
	<selected></selected>
	<image>paper43.jpg</image>
	<type>a</type>
	<area>other</area>
</article>
<article>
	<author>A. Barmpoutis</author>
	<title>Neural Network Fundamentals</title>
	<journal>Chapter 7 In Business Analytics: An Introduction, J. Liebowitz (ed.), Auerbach Publishers, Taylor &amp; Francis Group</journal>
	<urlvenue>http://www.routledge.com/books/details/9781466596092/</urlvenue>
	<month>January</month>
	<volume></volume>
	<number></number>
	<year>2014</year>
	<pages>179-202</pages>
	<urlpdf></urlpdf>
	<abstract>The learning objectives of this chapter are the following: The reader will understand the strengths and limitations of various types of artificial neural networks. Several representative neural network algorithms will be presented
and discussed in detail. Practical applications of neural networks will be explored by the reader through a set of exercises at the end of the chapter.</abstract>
	<selected></selected>
	<image>paper32.jpg</image>
	<type>bc</type>
	<area>nn</area>
</article>
<article>
	<author>A. Barmpoutis, B. DeVane, and J. C. Oliverio</author>
	<title>Applications of Virtual Environments in Experiential, STEM, and Health Science Education</title>
	<journal>Chapter 41 In Handbook of Virtual Environments: Design, Implementation, and Applications, Second Edition, K. Hale and K. Stanney (ed.), CRC press, Taylor &amp; Francis Group</journal>
	<urlvenue>http://www.taylorandfrancis.com/books/details/9781466511842/</urlvenue>
	<month>July</month>
	<volume></volume>
	<number></number>
	<year>2014</year>
	<pages>1055-1071</pages>
	<urlpdf></urlpdf>
	<abstract>This chapter presents examples of utilizing virtual environments for experiential learning and training purposes, with applications to several areas in the Science, Technology, Engineering &amp; Mathematics (STEM), and Health Sciences. The chapter starts with a general introduction to experiential learning, followed by a presentation of various technologies for enhancing the experience in virtual environments. The rest of the chapter is organized into two sections that discuss specific examples of virtual environments for experiential learning and therapeutic medical applications respectively. More specifically, the examples will demonstrate: the use of low-cost haptic devices in virtual environments for learning nanotechnology, experiential learning environments for forest education, the use of virtual reality theaters as an educational tool in the arts and the humanities, virtual environments for therapeutic solutions, interactive tools for treating motor disabilities using brain-computer interface for interaction with virtual environments, and experiential learning applications for microsurgical training using mixed reality and haptic feedback. The chapter concludes with a final section that discusses future research directions.</abstract>
	<selected></selected>
	<image>paper31.jpg</image>
	<type>bc</type>
	<area>other</area>
</article>
<article>
	<author>A. Kondyli, A. Barmpoutis, and V. Sisiopiku</author>
	<title>Investigation of the effect of drivers' body motion on traffic safety</title>
	<journal>University Transportation Center(UTC) Conference for the Southeast Region</journal>
	<urlvenue>http://www.nctspm.gatech.edu/2014Conference</urlvenue>
	<month>24-25 March</month>
	<volume></volume>
	<number></number>
	<year>2014</year>
	<pages></pages>
	<urlpdf></urlpdf>
	<abstract>A significant amount of research has been involved with the development of advanced driver-assistance systems. Such systems typically include radars, laser or video sensors that detect the vehicle trajectory and warn for an imminent lane departure, or sense the front vehicle's speed and apply the brakes of the following vehicle to maintain safe distance headways (e.g., collision avoidance system). However, most of these systems rely on the automobile position and do not consider the driver's actions during the driving task. In addition, the lane trajectory and position of the vehicle could potentially differ from the driver's intent to change lanes. Safety research has focused on eye tracking as a means of capturing driver's attention, fatigue, or drowsiness; however, the entire body posture has not been investigated in depth.
<br/><br/>
This presentation discusses a novel approach for studying the actual movements of drivers inside the vehicle, when performing specific maneuver types or while engaging to secondary tasks that require a certain body movement. With the use of two low-cost infrared depth sensors, the 3D shape of selected participants is being constructed, as they are performing various driving maneuvers and as they are engaged in secondary tasks while driving. The experiments are performed in real life conditions with the use of an instrumented vehicle owned by UF-Transportation Research Center. Eye-tracker glasses are used to enhance the data collection with gaze information. As part of the data analysis, the 3D point cloud time-series collected from the eye-tracker and the infrared sensors are analyzed using tensor-based models. A rigorous analysis of the results is expected to provide insights related to what drivers actually do (or do not do) that may trigger an unsafe event. A comparison between different driver groups (e.g., novice vs. elderly) will also be performed. 
<br/><br/>
The main objective of the work is to investigate the relationship between potentially unsafe driving events and the actual driver body posture and movements when performing a driving maneuver (e.g., lane changing, merging) under different traffic and geometric configurations and when engaging with a secondary task. The findings of this research are expected to provide insights regarding which body movements may hide unsafe situations while performing a driving maneuver that requires the attention of the surrounding environment. A second objective is to identify typical behaviors of specific driver groups (e.g., younger vs. older drivers, aggressive vs. conservative drivers, men vs. women), in naturalistic settings. Such information can be used for enhancing current driver training methods for targeted driver groups such as novice or elderly drivers. The third objective of the study is to develop a conceptual framework for constructing an in-vehicle driver-assistance system that takes into account the driver's body posture and movements rather than considering solely the vehicle position.
<br/><br/>
The presentation will introduce the study objectives and methodology and present preliminary results and expected benefits and implications from the research.
</abstract>
	<selected></selected>
	<image>paper42.jpg</image>
	<type>a</type>
	<area>3dcv</area>
</article>
<article>
	<author>A. Kondyli, V. Sisiopiku, L. Zhao, and A. Barmpoutis</author>
	<title>Comparative Analysis of Driving Maneuvers Using 3D Body Posture Data</title>
	<journal>Proceedings of the 5th International Conference on Applied Human Factors and Ergonomics AHFE (ed. T. Ahram, W. Karwowski and T. Marek)</journal>
	<urlvenue>http://www.ahfe2014.org/</urlvenue>
	<month>19-23 July</month>
	<volume></volume>
	<number></number>
	<year>2014</year>
	<pages>4416-4425</pages>
	<urlpdf>barmpoutis_ahfe14.pdf</urlpdf>
	<abstract>Research has shown that driver inattention is the most prevalent cause of traffic collisions accounting for an 
estimated 25 to 56% of crashes in the US. Driver inattention may result from drivers engagement in secondary 
activities (such as texting or cell-phone use), or lack of awareness of the surrounding environment. The main 
objective of this research is to investigate the relationship between potentially unsafe driving events and the actual 
driver body posture and movements when performing a driving maneuver under different traffic configurations. The 
paper presents results from a pilot study that captured the 3-D posture and activity of three drivers while performing 
both mandatory (merging) and discretionary (lane changing) maneuvers on freeway and arterial segments in 
Gainesville, Florida. The body posture of the drivers was captured through the use of a low-cost infrared depth 
sensor. A 7-point human skeletal model was fit to the captured depth frame sequences using our proposed 
framework. The comparative analysis of the participants' body movements while performing the maneuvers 
revealed differences between the participants' body activity when performing the same maneuvers. The findings of 
this research provide significant insights regarding which body movements may hide unsafe situations while 
performing a driving maneuver that requires the attention of the surrounding environment.</abstract>
	<selected></selected>
	<image>paper42.jpg</image>
	<type>c</type>
	<area>3dcv</area>
</article>
<article>
	<author>A. Barmpoutis, E. Fox, I. Elsner, and S. Flynn</author>
	<title>Augmented-reality environment for locomotor training in children with neurological injuries</title>
	<journal>In LNCS 8678 (Springer) Proceedings of MICCAI14 - Workshop on Augmented Environments for Computed Assisted Interventions: (eds. C.A. Linte, Z. Yaniv, P. Fallavollita, P. Abolmaesumi, and D. R. Holmes III)</journal>
	<urlvenue>http://campar.in.tum.de/AECAI/WebHome</urlvenue>
	<month>14 September</month>
	<volume></volume>
	<number></number>
	<year>2014</year>
	<pages>108-117</pages>
	<urlpdf>barmpoutis_miccai14.pdf</urlpdf>
	<abstract>In this paper a novel augmented-reality environment is presented for enhancing locomotor training. The main goal of this environment is to excite kids for walking and hence facilitate their locomotor therapy and at the same time provide the therapist with a quantitative framework for monitoring and evaluating the progress of the therapy. This paper focuses on the quantitative part of our framework, which uses a depth camera to capture the patient's body motion. More specifically, we present a model-free graph-based segmentation algorithm that detects the regions of the arms and legs in the depth frames. Then, we analyze their motion patterns in real-time by extracting various features such as the pace, length of stride, symmetry of walking pattern, and arm-leg synchronization. Several experimental results are presented that demonstrate the efficacy and robustness of the proposed methods.</abstract>
	<selected></selected>
	<image>paper43.jpg</image>
	<type>c</type>
	<area>3dcv</area>
</article>
<article>
	<author>R. Gallen, D. Eastop, E. Bozia, and A. Barmpoutis</author>
	<title>Digital imaging: the application of shape-from-shading to lace, seals and metal objects</title>
	<journal>Journal of the Institute of Conservation</journal>
	<urlvenue>http://dx.doi.org/10.1080/19455224.2014.999004</urlvenue>
	<month></month>
	<volume></volume>
	<number></number>
	<year>2015</year>
	<pages></pages>
	<urlpdf>http://www.tandfonline.com/eprint/KNTbk33ku7PzYWPKbTcr/full</urlpdf>
	<abstract>This article explores one application of a digital imaging technique to historic objects and online delivery of the virtual object. Shape-from-shading is a computer algorithm used to reconstruct three-dimensional shapes from two-dimensional images. The Digital Epigraphy and Archaeology (DEA) project used shape-from-shading to develop a digital website and toolbox to enhance computer-assisted examination of inscriptions preserved as ektypa. This article reports the results of a project to see if the DEA website and toolbox could be used with other materials and objects with information-rich textured surfaces. Seventeen samples were tested, including lace-like textiles placed on different backing materials; wax seal impressions made from a range of materials; and excavated metals. It was found that image capture with a flatbed scanner achieved better results than a multi-functional printer, and that the unprocessed flatbed scan images were sometimes more informative than digital photographs. It was possible to modify the DEA algorithm for both the lace-like samples and the seal impressions to obtain good three-dimensional (3D) reconstructed images. However, this was not possible with the metal samples due to the nature of the material. The 3D reconstructed images are useful to online users in providing an interactive resource that can be manipulated by the user, rather than a two-dimensional (2D) image.</abstract>
	<selected></selected>
	<image>paper60.jpg</image>
	<type>j</type>
	<area>dh</area>
</article>
<article>
	<author>A. Kondyli, V. Sisiopiku, L. Zhao, and A. Barmpoutis</author>
	<title>Comparative Analysis of Driving Maneuvers Using 3D Body Posture Data</title>
	<journal>Chapter 2 in Section 15 of Advances in Human Aspects of Transportation: Part II (ed. N. Stanton, S. Landry, G. Di Bucchianico, A. Vallicelli) ISBN: 978-1-4951-2098-5</journal>
	<urlvenue></urlvenue>
	<month>19 July</month>
	<volume></volume>
	<number></number>
	<year>2014</year>
	<pages>194-203</pages>
	<urlpdf></urlpdf>
	<abstract>Research has shown that driver inattention is the most prevalent cause of traffic collisions accounting for an 
estimated 25 to 56% of crashes in the US. Driver inattention may result from drivers engagement in secondary 
activities (such as texting or cell-phone use), or lack of awareness of the surrounding environment. The main 
objective of this research is to investigate the relationship between potentially unsafe driving events and the actual 
driver body posture and movements when performing a driving maneuver under different traffic configurations. The 
paper presents results from a pilot study that captured the 3-D posture and activity of three drivers while performing 
both mandatory (merging) and discretionary (lane changing) maneuvers on freeway and arterial segments in 
Gainesville, Florida. The body posture of the drivers was captured through the use of a low-cost infrared depth 
sensor. A 7-point human skeletal model was fit to the captured depth frame sequences using our proposed 
framework. The comparative analysis of the participants' body movements while performing the maneuvers 
revealed differences between the participants' body activity when performing the same maneuvers. The findings of 
this research provide significant insights regarding which body movements may hide unsafe situations while 
performing a driving maneuver that requires the attention of the surrounding environment.</abstract>
	<selected></selected>
	<image>paper42.jpg</image>
	<type>bc</type>
	<area>3dcv</area>
</article>
<article>
	<author>Mingran Li, Yingjie Chen, and A. Barmpoutis</author>
	<title>Collaborative Learning in Video Games to Enhance Learning Efficiency</title>
	<journal>122nd Annual Conference of the American Society for Engineering Education </journal>
	<urlvenue>http://www.asee.org/conferences-and-events/conferences/annual-conference/2015</urlvenue>
	<month>14-17 June</month>
	<volume></volume>
	<number></number>
	<year>2015</year>
	<pages></pages>
	<urlpdf></urlpdf>
	<abstract></abstract>
	<selected></selected>
	<image>paper1.jpg</image>
	<type>a</type>
	<area></area>
</article>
<article>
	<author>E. Schaefer, A. Barmpoutis, E. Tripp, and S. L. Quincy</author>
	<title>Teaching Carolingian Chant with Interactive Software: Theory, Application &amp; Assessment</title>
	<journal>8th Annual Conference for the Scholarship of Teaching and Learning</journal>
	<urlvenue>http://academics.georgiasouthern.edu/ce/conferences/sotlcommons/</urlvenue>
	<month>25-27 March</month>
	<volume></volume>
	<number></number>
	<year>2015</year>
	<pages></pages>
	<urlpdf></urlpdf>
	<abstract>The science of teaching/learning and the development of interactive technology are now at a stage where an effective interactive system can be developed for the teaching and learning of the basic vocabulary and grammar of early musical notation systems. Our interdisciplinary team is developing the first such system, in addition to the first assessment tool for evaluating the effectiveness of the system. We propose to offer a presentation session that will include the following: an explanation of the software and the learning research behind it; a demonstrate of the system; an explanation of the assessment process used to determine the effectiveness of the software; an audience participation segment in which audience members will see a short demonstration video regarding a particular segment of the notation work in self-correcting, interactive exercises take an online assessment.
Participants in this presentation session will gain an understanding of the benefits of interactive learning; gain an understanding of an assessment process for an interactive learning that also provides a framework for ensuring an unbiased assessment; have an experience of a new interactive software, the principals behind which could be applied to various disciplines.</abstract>
	<selected></selected>
	<image>paper1.jpg</image>
	<type>a</type>
	<area></area>
</article>
<article>
	<author>J. Oliverio, A. Barmpoutis, C. Juehring, and A. Yudin</author>
	<title>Enhancing Global Collaboration Through Network-empowered Live Performance</title>
	<journal>Conference on Electronic Visualization and the Arts</journal>
	<urlvenue>http://www.eva-london.org/</urlvenue>
	<month>7-9 July</month>
	<volume></volume>
	<number></number>
	<year>2015</year>
	<pages></pages>
	<urlpdf></urlpdf>
	<abstract>Research and development of real-time arts performance systems has been underway at the University of Florida Digital Worlds Institute since 2001. Significant attributes of this research include the successful facilitation of synchronous global-scale performing arts events, the evolution of process and practice for arts and engineering collaborations between multi-point performance sites across the high-speed network, and the development and utilization of a unique toolkit of techniques and technologies. 
<br/><br/>
Examples of our global-scale networked performances include: the synchronous musical union of ethnic performers located in seven cities across five continents for 'In Common: Time' at SIGGRAPH 2005; a quartet of modern dancers located in four remote cities across Asia and North American motion-captured and mapped into a single shared Cartesian coordinate space performing on virtual percussion instruments with 3D audio in 'Same Space Same Time' (2010); the integration of multiple remote audiences providing character choices and feedback on their mobile devices (aggregated, visualized and given to the performers in real-time) during a multi-continental performance featuring network-attached Kinect devices driving synchronous representations of the distributed performers in a gaming engine for 'Icons of Innovation' at IDMAA 2012. 
<br/><br/>
In addition to developing the methodologies necessary to integrate various traditional and emergent technologies into these multi-faceted real-time performance systems, a number of novel techniques and collaborative relationships have resulted from this work. Using several of our distributed performances as exemplars, we will outline and then detail the esthetic, procedural, technological, and logistic considerations inherent in working with artists, engineers, and media producers across multiple time zones, cultures, and sub-nets. 
<br/><br/>
We have learned a considerable number of lessons that can optimize the strategic planning and implementation of distributed performing arts events, and will offer not only background and recommendations for those interested in working in this space, but also examples of the specific tools, techniques and technologies we have developed and integrated into the design and production of this work. </abstract>
	<selected></selected>
	<image>paper1.jpg</image>
	<type>a</type>
	<area></area>
</article>
<article>
	<author>A. Kondyli, V. Sisiopiku, A. Barmpoutis</author>
	<title>Analyzing 3D Body Posture Activity during Merging and Lane Changing Maneuvers</title>
	<journal>2015 Road Safety &amp; Simulation International Conference</journal>
	<urlvenue>http://stc.utk.edu/STCevents/rss2015/</urlvenue>
	<month>6-8 October</month>
	<volume></volume>
	<number></number>
	<year>2015</year>
	<pages></pages>
	<urlpdf></urlpdf>
	<abstract>Although significant advances have been done with respect to vehicle technology and roadway construction, driver behavior remains the number one contributing factor of traffic crashes worldwide. Studies show that one of the major causes of crashes is driver inattention. Driver inattention may occur when drivers are involved with secondary activities (e.g., texting, talking on the phone, or eating), and when they fail to follow the cues of the surrounding environment while driving.  The latter is particularly important when drivers are negotiating maneuvers and are required to interact with other vehicles as in the case of changing lanes or merging onto the freeway. <br/><br/>
The main objective of this research is to investigate the relationship between driver behavior and safety, by looking at the actual body movements and posture, as well as the eye fixation of the drivers when they are performing lane changing and merging maneuvers under different traffic conditions. To accomplish this objective, a total of 34 drivers were recruited to participate in an instrumented vehicle field study, where each participant drove for approximately two hours along a pre-selected route. The participants were instructed to perform both mandatory (merging) and discretionary (lane changing) maneuvers on freeway and arterial segments in Gainesville, Florida.  During the data collection experiment, the participants? body posture was recorded with the use of a low-cost infrared depth sensor (Microsoft Kinect). The sensor was able to capture video and depth sequences, which were eventually converted to a 3D video. In addition to the body posture information, the participants? eye gaze throughout the entire data collection effort was also recorded with the help of an eye-tracking equipment. Lastly, the instrumented vehicle was equipped with two cameras that faced the front and the rear, and therefore, information about the traffic conditions during the data collection period was stored through these cameras.
<br/><br/>A rich dataset of driver behavior was developed and analyzed as part of this research. The analysis findings relate the 3D sequence of driver motion and posture with the actual eye and head movement of drivers, specifically for cases where drivers fail to identify the surrounding vehicles. The paper presents the research approach, summarizes findings, and provides recommendations for enhancing vehicle design aspects and driver training programs. The findings are expected to assist in establishing monitoring guidelines for advanced driver assistance systems that take into account the driver?s body position and movements, rather than considering solely the vehicle position relative to other vehicles on the road. The results can also assist in developing appropriate alert mechanisms for increasing driver alertness.</abstract>
	<selected></selected>
	<image>paper42.jpg</image>
	<type>a</type>
	<area>3dcv</area>
</article>
<article>
	<author>A. Barmpoutis, E. Bozia, and D. Fortuna</author>
	<title>Interactive 3D digitization, retrieval, and analysis of ancient sculptures, using infrared depth sensors for mobile devices</title>
	<journal>17th International Conference on Human-Computer Interaction</journal>
	<urlvenue>http://2015.hci.international/</urlvenue>
	<month>2-7 August</month>
	<volume></volume>
	<number></number>
	<year>2015</year>
	<pages></pages>
	<urlpdf>barmpoutis_hcii15.pdf</urlpdf>
	<abstract>In this paper a novel framework is presented for interactive feature-based retrieval and visualization of human statues, using depth sensors for mobile devices. A skeletal model is fitted to the depth image of a statue or human body in general and is used as a feature vector that captures the pose variations in a given collection of skeleton data. A scale- and twist- invariant distance function is defined in the feature space and is employed in a topology-preserving low-dimensional lattice mapping framework. The user can interact with this self-organizing map by submitting queries in the form of a skeleton from a statue or a human body. The proposed methods are demonstrated in a real dataset of 3D digitized Graeco-Roman statues from Palazzo Altemps.</abstract>
	<selected></selected>
	<image>paper62.jpg</image>
	<type>c</type>
	<area>dh</area>
</article>
<article>
	<author>A. Kondyli, V. Sisiopiku, L. Zhao, and A. Barmpoutis</author>
	<title>Computer assisted analysis of drivers' body activity using a range camera</title>
	<journal>IEEE Intelligent Transportation Systems Magazine</journal>
	<urlvenue>http://ieeexplore.ieee.org/xpl/RecentIssue.jsp?punumber=5117645</urlvenue>
	<month>(forthcoming)</month>
	<volume></volume>
	<number></number>
	<year>2015</year>
	<pages></pages>
	<urlpdf>barmpoutis_ieeeits15.pdf</urlpdf>
	<abstract>A significant amount of research has been involved with the development of advanced driver-assistance systems. Such systems typically include radars, laser or video sensors that detect the vehicle trajectory and warn for an imminent lane departure, or sense the front vehicle's speed and apply the brakes of the following vehicle to maintain safe distance headways (i.e., collision avoidance system). However, most of these systems rely on the subject vehicle and surrounding vehicles' position and do not explicitly consider the driver's actions during the driving task. In addition, safety research has focused on eye tracking as a means of capturing driver's attention, fatigue, or drowsiness; however, the body posture has not been investigated in depth. This paper presents a novel approach for studying the actual movements of drivers inside the vehicle, when performing specific maneuver types such as lane changing and merging. A pilot study was conducted along a freeway and arterial segment, where the 3D shapes of selected participants were constructed with the use of Microsoft Kinect range camera while merging and changing lanes. A 7-point human skeletal model was fit to the captured range data (depth frame sequences) using the proposed framework. The analysis of the captured 3D data showed that there are important differences between participants when performing similar driving maneuvers. The preliminary results of this pilot research set the basis for implementing the proposed methodological framework for conducting full-scale experiments with a variety of participants, and exploring differences due to driver behavior attributes, such as age, gender and driving experience. </abstract>
	<selected></selected>
	<image>paper42.jpg</image>
	<type>j</type>
	<area>3dcv</area>
</article>
</articles>